       ACCIDENTAL TRANSIENTS

Everything was going pretty badly at my baba's house— 
 endless messes, zero privacy, constant mooning and 
 pranks—and I was considering moving out for the
fourth time in one day when my brother Ibrahim decided 
to move back home with his new Catholic wife, Dorothy. 
They're only twenty-one and Dorothy wouldn't have sex 
with him unless they got married. Leave it to my brother to 
marry a good Arab chick in disguise.
I had just pulled into the farm and was lugging my man- 
nequin head into the house when I found out about this. 
I use the head when I teach at Moda College. My parents 
once hoped I would become a scientist, marry an Arab 
(even though there are none around), pop out three or 
four kids, and win the Nobel Prize for science. Instead,

'HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                          RANDA JARRAR

 I'm a hairstylist and I teach on the side. Today's class was  without marrying her. And now, we were all to welcome 
 on blowouts.                                                  them "home."
   I snuck past my little little brother, Jaseem, the twin; he   I stood up, the mannequin head still in my arms. "And 
 was practicing his hoodlum walk in the field, one jean-leg    what the hell say do I have in this? This is my house too, 
 rolled up to the knee, his baseball cap tilted to the side.   Baba. Where do you get aaaff telling Catholic brides they're 
 When he saw me and the mannequin head, he shrieked.           welcome in my house?" I have a Michigan accent. I can't 
 Then, he told me the news.                                    help it.
   "His wife?"                                                   "Ya binti, no need to be waving your doll head around. 
   "And . . . he changed his name to Abe." The lettering on    Abe is welcome here, and so is Dorothy. Let's make peace . 
 Jaseem's cap spelled out "5-a-Day!" He was practicing to be   and dinner."
 a hoodlum in a fruit-intake-awareness hat.                      "I'll be damned. Who the hell is Abe? Last I checked 
   I turned in a huff and walked up to the door. I am a        your son's name was Ibrahim."
 twenty-nine-year-old virgin and still living at home on a       "I changed the name Mama gave me to the name I wanted." 
 farm in Jackson, seventy-five miles away from any Arabs.        "Phhh," I said. "You changed your Arabic name to the 
 Baba says he wants us to be our own, self-sustaining com-     name of some nerdy Jewish accountant?"
 munity. That means I take care of all the humans, while         "Whatever, your name is so hard to pronounce, Dina, 
 Baba tends to the one surviving goat, the horseless sta-      I'm sure you understand."
 ble, the chickens, and the two peacocks, which fly up and       The twins squealed with delight and did ninja kicks on 
 scratch you in the face if you mess with them. Peacocks       the rug. I went to the other side of the house, into the read- 
 think they're fancier than chickens, but they're not; they    ing room, flipped on a light and pretended to read a kilt cat- 
 still have to live in a coop no matter how hot their feathers alog. I looked at the male models' hairy legs, wishing I had 
 look.                                                         just married some dude. But every single guy I have ever 
                                                               tried to date was chased away by Jaseem's pranks, Waseem's 
 Abe and his new wife sat on the couch silently as Baba ex-    excessive nerdiness, and Baba's rudeness: he would reply to 
 plained the situation to us. My brother had disappeared,      my dates' "Is Dina home?" by hanging up the telephone or 
 with almost no notice, a year earlier. He had graduated col-  slamming the door in their (handsome) faces. I simmered 
 lege early and thought his genius ass belonged in Lansing,    over how easily he'd accepted Dorothy, put my foot up on 
 working for the state. That is where he met Dorothy. Ap-      the chest we used for a coffee table, and noticed a dead bird 
 parently, he wasn't enough of a genius to get into her pants  taped to a piece of cardboard a few inches away from me.

 98                                                                                                           99

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                                RANDA JARRAR

   "Waseem," I yelled out. "What the hell is this dead bird         "I like dem. Dey look like Lubbriculus variegatu " Was- 
doing in the reading room?"                                      eem said.
   Waseem came in, his thick glasses resting on the bridge          I stood before the now hung-up, framed, dead humming- 
of his perpetually dripping nose. "I found it in the field. It's bird and waited.
a hubbingbird."                                                     Waseem picked his nose.
   "I can see that," I said. I picked up the cardboard and          "Thank you?" I said. "Freakin' thank you would be nice." 
stared at the bird. The hummingbird's feathers glowed iri-          "Thanks, Dida," he said and walked off, in search of more 
descent green and blue, like the lake in summertime, and         treasure.
the neck was dotted red. Its wings were still, for once, and 
dark. The entire creature was the size of two thumbs.            In the kitchen, I sprinkled a frozen casserole with rosemary 
   Waseem took the bird from me and slowly placed it in          sprigs from the garden and baked the dish at 350 degrees. I 
the middle of a thick, empty wooden frame. He brought out        waited, listening to the egg timer tick. Outside, a punk-rock- 
 a hammer and nail and asked me to help him hang it up           looking bird hooked its claws around the fence: a Ruby- 
 along with the rest of his framed "miracle discoveries" that    crowned Kinglet. The grayish-brown bird had, at the very 
 lined the reading room's walls: a butterfly in mid-chrysalis,   tip of its head, a red flame mohawk. I wished my customers 
 a stray sock that belonged to no one in the house that he'd     at the salon were as adventurous.
 found on a peacock one afternoon (I was sure this was not          I have a thing for birds. When I was a kid, I used to watch 
 a miracle, but a Jaseem prank), a doll's eye he uncovered in    them through my thick binoculars for hours, and kept a bird 
 the coop but was sure belonged to a chicken, and a myste-       journal with a red feather, from a Red-throated Loon, taped 
 rious little bell he found in a big flower at the edge of the   to the front cover. I loved the Mute Swan, which some- 
 property.                                                       times glided across the pond on our property; the Vermilion 
    I handed him a pencil and asked him to mark where            Flycatcher and the Yellow-crowned Night-Heron, which 
 he thought the dead hummingbird should hang. He left a          alighted on the wooden fence on early fall mornings; the 
 small lead mark on the wall, between a picture of Ibrahim       little field sparrows and the dark, slutty-sounding Harlequin 
 and the chrysalis. I hammered the nail in while looking at      Ducks. On Sundays, while my mother took care of the baby 
 my brother's photo. "Can you believe he has the nerve to get    twins and Ibrahim tried to break into my room, I hid inside 
 married? And move back home?"                                   my tent and read an encyclopedia about birds. I loved the 
    "I like his new bustache," Waseem said, ignoring me.         name of the Swallow-tailed Kite most, and one afternoon, 
    "Mustaches are for old dignitaries and cops."                when I came home from school, Baba took me to the coop

  100                                                                                                             101

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                         RANDA JARRAR

and showed me one, a white bird with ink-black-bordered        "I've never seen you without it," I said.
wings which had accidentally flown to Michigan. We stood       "You want me to shave my mustache, you coiffera. Well, 
together in the smelly coop watching the new bird, and I     I won't. Ever. Well ... if Palestine ever becomes a state, I 
worried about how it would get home, but I didn't want to    will shave it."
ask Baba, fearing he'd launch into a sad speech about Pal-     "I don't ever want Palestine to be a state," Jaseem said. 
estine. I still remember him crouched by the cage, his smil- "Because you'll make us move there."
ing, then-young face. I took out my journal and noted both     "Don't be silly," Baba said. "We will never move there. 
the bird and my baba as accidental transients.               We live here.
  Now, the only Loons I see are my bridal customers, who       "But why dot?" Waseem said. In addition to reading 
scream and plead for thicker, more voluminous hairpieces.    organic-chem books, he was peeking at some Chomsky on 
                                                             the side.-
The timer buzzed and I took out the casserole, brought out     "Because I don't belong there anymore," said Baba. 
the plates and silverware, and called everyone to supper.      "On the telephone-box-sized land," I said.
They came in sheepishly, and Baba cracked open a bottle of     "I told you never to mention my land again," Baba said, 
brandy to celebrate Abe's marriage. I rolled my eyes. Doro-  waving an asparagus spear in my direction.
thy sat and waited for the food to come to her. I wanted to    "Sorry, Baba," I said.
throw a drumstick at her freckled face.                        "Jesus loves the Palestinians," Dorothy said. The table 
   "Dida says you have a stupid bustach " Waseem told        went silent. We are the kind of Muslims who pray for tax 
Abe.                                                         breaks (Baba), Nintendo DS games (Jaseem), anatomy col- 
   "So does she," Abe said.                                  oring books (Waseem), pussy (Abe), and a guilt-free con- 
   "I never said that. Waseem is hallucinating."             science to move the fuck out of the house (Yours Truly). 
   "You said they were for old digbaberries or something."   The only thing keeping us from being outright atheists is 
   "Yes. Like Baba."                                         that none of us had ever eaten pork. We were bound to God 
   "I love my mustache," Baba said, cutting the casserole    through the absence of pig grease.
 into six perfectly even pieces. Baba likes equality. This is   And some Palestinians love him, Baba said, swigging 
 because when his parents died, he inherited a piece of land brandy. "You ought to take Dorothy to Nazareth sometime," 
 big enough to build a telephone booth on, while his broth-  he said to Abe.
 ers inherited acres and acres of olive trees.                 "Yes, and no one there would bat an eye. Imagine me taking 
   "I love it too," Dorothy said.                            my Christian white boyfriend back to Palestine with me?" I said.

 102                                                                                                       103

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                                   RANDA JARRAR

  "You have a boyfriend?" Jaseem gasped dramatically.                I was then tasked with caring for the guys. I made break- 
Everyone laughed and banged the table with their palms. I          fast every morning, packed their sack lunches, and alternated 
got up and left the kitchen.                                       cooking dinner with Baba. This had less to do with my need 
  "Come back," Baba shouted after me. "Really, it won't be         to be a good Arab girl and more to do with our collective 
the same without you. Who would do the dishes?" They all           need, as a family, to have a house that was not on fire. The 
roared again, and I felt their laughs sink into my back and        one morning I was running late and the boys had to make 
my shoulders as I climbed the stone stairs up to my room.          their own breakfasts, they chose Peeps, baked on top of Pop- 
I heard their laughing voices, all except for Dorothy's, be-       Tarts. The gooey mess dripped down to the base of the oven 
cause she knew that now the dishwashing would fall to her.         and promptly caught on fire. An hour later, half a dozen 
                                                                   firemen were drinking strong ahwe with my baba, who wore 
My mama is no longer with us. I wish I could tell you she          an apron and served the strong coffee to them out of small 
died romantically of a staph infection she contracted from a       demitasses on a silver tray. Never mind that he never served 
patient at the hospital; that we couldn't fly her to Palestine,    me coffee this way: I was the one who would have to wash 
couldn't watch her body rot as we waited to get through            all those glasses and dishes up.
checkpoints, so we buried her in Hollow Cemetery; that 
her name is a bright and weightless leaf on the headstone —        I drove a half hour to the salon the next morning, blasting 
Selima Amir; that we visit her grave on Saturdays.                 the stereo and letting my hair fly out of the cracked win- 
   But she is literally no longer with us. She left us for a Japa- dow. I'm a co-owner of The Jeweled Crown. We do hair, 
nese entrepreneur who was in Detroit to check out Ford's out-      massage, nails, makeup, hair removal, as well as hair and 
put of hybrid SUVs; the suits took him for a drive in the coun-    makeup for weddings and other special events. Recently, we 
try and hit a deer. He ended up at our local hospital, where       hired a muhajjaba hair stylist, Jauhara, who rented out one 
Mama was his nurse. She helped heal his broken ribs and            of the rooms we reserved for massages, to do other muhaj- 
nursed him back to health; he returned the favor by giving         jabat's hair in the privacy of the room. Turns out chicks who 
her a three-carat ring and asking her to run away with him to      wear hijab like to get their hair•done more often than chicks 
Osaka. Her shift ended at six in the morning, and by the time      who don't.
we woke up at seven thirty, she had already packed her things        Our master colorist, a boy named Keith, is trans. Other 
and left. She never said goodbye to me, just scrawled a note on    stylists sometimes ask him how "it works," and when he of- 
the corner of my birding journal: "You won't understand," as if    fers to show them, they giggle wildly. Once, a muhajjaba 
it were an order. And, just like that, Mama had flown the coop.    wanted to get her hair colored by him, since he's a much

 104                                                                                                                  1 0 C

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                             RANDA JARRAR

better colorist than Jauhara. He flat-out refused, because she   A few hours later, we were spraying the bridesmaids' 
obviously thought that Keith wasn't really a man. Eventu-      poofy crowns and wishing for superpowers. Have you ever 
ally, the exotic hotness of doing a veiled woman's hair took   tried to please a bride? You'd be wishing for them too.
over and Keith abandoned his moral and ethical objections        "Which would you rather have," Keith said, "flight or in- 
and got down with the peach-blonde lowlights.                  visibility?"
  They all rib me for living at my baba's house and taking       "Flight," I said, without thinking.
care of the boys. The only consolation is that I am saving all   "I hate heights, so I'd choose invisibility."
my money, and one day I'll be able to live in my own house.      "I don't believe it. You're the most extroverted bitch I 
They don't know I've already saved enough money to buy         know," I said. "And wouldn't you want to fly all over the 
two shacks in Detroit and a barn in the UP if I want to.       place, whenever you wanted?"
   "Speaking of weddings," I said, putting curlers into a        "Shit yeah," Keith said, "and I would. I'd fly first class on 
bridesmaid's hair, and told Keith and Jauhara about Ibra-      a Boeing to Paris. In those comfortable big seats that look 
him. They laughed so hard at his choice of wife and his        like fans."
name change the bridesmaids under the blow-dryer chairs          "I'd fly with my body. Then I could go whenever I wanted. 
heard them.                                                    I wouldn't have to wait for flights to take off."
  "You should teach those fools a lesson right now," Keith       "You've lived in Michigan all your life and you've never 
said, and move out."                                           even been to Toronto."
  I said that when I closed my eyes and imagined the guys liv-    "She would    Jauhara yelled, "to Balestine. She would
ing without me, I saw flames, or worse, fireman coffee parties.strab her bee-bull to her body and fly them over checkboints." 
  "You're afraid they'll burn or celebrate without you,"         "That would be nice. For about three seconds," Keith 
Keith teased.                                                  said, "then the army would shoot her down."
  "Live herrr alone, you estrange boy-gerrel," Jauhara said.     "He's right." I said. "But I still choose flight. And when he
"She's good gerrel. She'll leave when she finds good man to    flies to Paris, I'll float by his plane and flip him off."
marry.                                                           "I won't see you, 'cause I'll be wearing a cool satin eye-mask." 
  "I have," I said. "I'm marrying Keith."                        "That would make the stewardesses suspicious, don't you
  Keith rolled his eyes. He didn't believe in marriage.        think? A floating eye-mask?"
Whenever the women at the salon told him it was because          "Not as suspicious as Homeland Security would get 
he hadn't found the right person, he would laugh and say,      about your flying Arab ass. And they prefer to be called 
"A person won't change a patriarchal institution."             flight attendants now."

106                                                                                                            107

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                             RANDA JARRAR

  At the end of my shift I swept up the floor, which I like to mold. In the end, the headdress itself looked like a swan. 
do because it brings me comfort, like gathering stray strands  I was invited to the wedding to do the bride's hair on loca- 
in my mind. When I was done sweeping, I had a bagful           tion, and when she tossed the headdress like a bouquet 
of black-brown-red-blonde hair; the mixture looked like fur    into the crowd of female guests, I caught it, or maybe I 
from a full-body wax of Bigfoot.                               elbowed a couple of nine-year-old girls and dove to the 
  After work, I drove out to teach a seminar on up-dos. I      ground to catch it. That was four years ago. Since then, 
carried my mannequin head into Moda Hair Design Col-           I've made it my personal religious experience every Sun- 
lege and used a large, round brush with thousands of bristles  day to carefully paint just one headdress feather. Some 
on it to show a dozen women how to give their customers        of the feathers are sky blue, some coral; a few are mer- 
big, bouncy crowns. "You could have been an ornitholo-         maid's tail, hummingbird's neck, and seaweed colored. I 
gist," Mama's phantom voice curled into my ear, and I si-      am painting today's feather bright red.
lently snapped back, "I am an artist." The thirteen blow-        While I set the feather to dry, Dorothy knocked on 
dryers hummed loudly, and I lectured to the girls over the     my door. I knew it was Dorothy because I've memorized 
noise.                                                         everyone's knocks, and Dorothy's was feminine, sweet, al- 
                                                               most like my mama's. I hesitated to let her in.
Waseem and Jaseem were punching and kicking each                 "Dina. I just want to talk."
other in the field. I could see them from my bedroom             "About what?"
window. Abe and Dorothy came home and everyone ate               A long, tumbleweed-across-the-landscape silence. 
barbeque on the cold patio. I refused to join them. In-          "My hair."
stead, I used my old bird-watching binoculars and spied          A few seconds later, she was on my cushion-topped seat 
on them as they dined like a family. I drew the shades,        in front of the antique dresser and mirror. I ran a bright-red 
finally, and took out my headdress from the closet. Some       brush through her hair.
people have meditation, some drugs, some shopping: I             "What do you want to do with it?" Her long, straight, 
have this headdress. A bride came in once and asked me         brown tresses hung limply against her modest breasts. 
for a swan-like crown for her wedding. She was a dancer at       "Something simple. A trim?"
some Greek-town casino and had a strong showgirl-head-           "A what? I don't do trims. I do transfor-mations." I put a 
gear aesthetic. She brought in a headdress from one of her     hand on my hip and waited.
acts so I could model her swan-crown after it. I spent three     "I'm scared."
weeks gluing white Mute Swan feathers onto the plastic           44 can tell," I sang.

 108                                                                                                           109

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                                     RANDA JARRAR

   "What should I do?"                                                "How could you?" Ibrahim yelled up at me. "Aren't you 
   "Well, what have you always wanted but were scared to            supposed to know how to cut hair?"
do?" I said. I waited while she bit the inside of her cheek.          "And aren't you supposed to know how to treat a wife? 
   "Something punk," she whispered. "Like, crazy. Short."           Huh. I guess it's hereditary," I said.
   I knew exactly what she was talking about. I took out the          "That is unfair," Baba said. "Your mother's leaving had 
clippers.                                                           nothing to do with the way I mistreated her."
   At first I was thinking less Ruby-crowned Kinglet and              We all looked at him.
more Flock of Seagulls. But the more I talked to Dorothy,             "Besides," Baba said, "you have done a terrible shit in 
the more I liked her. She was from a motherless family too,         Dorothy's hair."
and she wanted to be a landscape photographer. Her father             Dorothy screamed from upstairs.
had kept her from going to college. She was still very fond           "You are all,ridiculous," I said. Waseem pouted. "Except 
 of him. I cut and cut and I blow-dried and added shine and         you, Waseem." Jaseem hung his head down. "And you, Jas- 
 gel and mousse and styled and styled. When I was done, she         eem. God. If you keep making these faces I'll never move 
 gasped at her reflection ecstatically.                             into my own house."
   We descended the steps, Dorothy slowly, like a princess,           "Leaving home," Ibrahim said, sounding like some mo- 
 her bitch-in-waiting. I liked it. I hadn't felt girly in the house tivational speaker, "should have a lot more to do with your 
 in years, not since Mama and I played dress-up or did our          ability to be independent and less to do with the faces some 
 nails together.                                                    kids make."
   Slowly, a hush fell over the boys in the living room, and          "Whoa. Did you just try to advise me? I'm twenty-nine. Go 
 Abe looked up at Dorothy. She flung her arms up, finally,          to hell," I said, then ran to my room and slammed the door.
 and said, "What do you think?"                                       Dorothy was sitting on my bed, flattening the points I had 
    "Your hair looks like . ," Waseem started.                      sculpted into her hair.
    "A picnic basket," Jaseem finished.                               "I don't want to be married," she said.
    "More like picnic leftovers," Ibrahim whispered.                  "It's never too late to annul it," I said.
    Dorothy ran back up the stairs.                                   "I guesS I could do that. I'm not really that Catholic," she 
    "How could you?" I said, directing my voice at all four         said, and stroked my headdress, which I had left out on my 
 of them. I was standing at the very first step. I looked like a    bed. Soon, she was flattening the points I had sculpted into 
 queen atop a staircase made from cut rock and diamonds,            the feathers, so I reached over her and picked up the crown, 
 the boys, my misbehaved servants.                                  and walked it to the closet.

 110

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                             RANDA JARRAR

   "Sorry. This headdress is my religion," I said.               "Dorothy, baby, come on," Ibrahim pleaded. "I didn't 
   She nodded, and fresh tears streamed down her freckled      mean anything I said."
cheeks.                                                          "Gaa a-eh," she yelled. Baba's bourbon bottle glinted a 
                                                               few hand-lengths away from the headdress.
Ibrahim begged and yelled and Dorothy yelled back all            "I totally respect Dorothy's need to be alone," I said, 
night. I hid in my room and waited for morning.                slowly creeping up to her. "I'm just gonna grab this real 
   Sometime around dawn, I heard one of the twins bang         quick."
 down my door. Jaseem. It was his signature three-knock, one     She clasped her hands around the swan-crown. "Nuuuh," 
 tap. I got out of bed and shuffled across the room, noticing  she said. "I kee is on til m- hair gow back," she said.
 that my closet was wide open. Jaseem burst into the room.       Baba shrugged and went back to the house. Waseem and 
 "Dorothy is missing," he said.                                 aseem followed. I saw that I would never get my headdress 
   "Oh, joy." I scratched my bed-knotted hair.                 back if she was going to be stubborn about it, so I decided 
   "We're off on an excavation.                                to hide out in the barn until Dorothy passed out again. I 
   "He beans a search expedition," Waseem popped up            told Ibrahim I would take care of her, and soon he was off 
 from behind him.                                              to bed, too.
   I threw on my robe and we navigated the dark house,           A few minutes later, Dorothy stirred. "Weh I leaveeen to- 
 looking for Dorothy. Baba and Ibrahim held one flashlight     maa," she slurred.
 each, and Ibrahim tried to blame the whole thing on me.         "I'm leaving, too In a few hours."
   "Women are very sensitive about losing their hair,"           "Fo g000d?"
 said.                                                           "For work," I said. A few minutes later she was snoring, 
   "And about their husbands telling them it looks like shit," and I was thinking, Poor Dorothy. She couldn't survive for 
 I shot back.                                                  a day in that house, and I've survived twenty-nine years. I 
   We tried the garage, the basement, the field, the stables,  slowly peeled the rainbow swan from her. head.
 and finally the chicken coop. The chicken and peacocks          I crept back into my room, the headdress in my arms. Just 
 sounded their horns at us. We shone our flashlights until our to be safe, I decided to take it with me to work, in case Doro- 
 beams landed on a strange-looking bird, a multi-colored swan. thy went through with her plan to escape with it.
   Dorothy was wearing the crown on her head, and hiding 
 her body under a pile of hay.                                 I wore the crown on my drive to Detroit, just after dawn, and 
   "Lea me alone, allo you," she slurred.                      thought of a folktale Mama used to tell me when I was little,

 112                                                                                                           113

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                              RANDA JARRAR

about a couple Who longed for a daughter but had three sons.       "You must be really free at that farm," she said.
They prayed for a girl day and night; they begged God to send      I laughed•and told her I was the nanny and the maid. 
them any girl at all, even if she was a ghoul. Nine months         "Do you have a boyfriend?" she whispered.
later, the wife gave birth to a daughter. The three boys hated     "No," I whispered back.
their little sister and believed she really was a ghoul, and one   "I do. But don't tell anyone." We were miles away from 
night accused her of eating the family's lambs, which had       Dearborn but she was worried someone at the salon would 
gone missing, one by one, from the family farm. Sad and         know someone who knew someone who knew her parents. 
scared, she struck out on her own. She wandered aimlessly       Hey, it's happened.
throughout the land, until she found a magical nightingale in      "Are you seeing him tonight?" I said.
a cage. She freed it and, for a reward, the nightingale gave her   "Yeah. But when he picks me up, I have to lean my seat 
a home of her own. I stopped at a drive-thru donut place and    all the way back so no one on Warren Avenue sees me with 
drowned my jealousy in powdered sugar and raspberry jelly.      him."
   My first customer of the day was a teenager from Dearborn.      "Are you serious? You have to lean back the car seat? You 
I braced myself for the therapy session I'd have to offer. Some have to vanish?"
customers want to talk, and others want to rant—a hairdress-       She gave me a grave look and nodded, as I put her hair 
er can tell almost immediately which one is in her chair. The   through the ceramic straightening iron.
customer who wants silence rarely graces me with her pres- 
ence, and even when she does, she usually asks how I ended         I drove home that night and thought of what my life 
up doing hair. The teenager's name was Lamia. She wanted        would be like if we'd lived in Dearborn, or if I lived there 
her hair straightened, and when I tried to dissuade her, saying now. People would never talk about me on Warren Avenue: 
all she needed was a haircut and her curls would be bouncy,     who would care? Or maybe they would. As oppressive as my 
she wouldn't hear it. She wanted straight, shiny hair.          baba and our family was, my seat had never been leaned 
   I washed and conditioned her hair, listening to her try to   back. I had never had to vanish.
figure out why my family lives in Jackson. "My baba always         On the back roads just outside Chelsea, a flock of Sand- 
wanted to live on a farm," I said. "He grew up on one."         hill Cranes congregated in the middle of the road. I slowed 
   "My dad grew up in a shack on a mountain in Sidon,"          down but knew they'd fly away as I approached, and they 
she said. "But he still has to work and have Lebanese people    did: all but one. It was heavy on top, with long, spindly legs, 
around him."                                                    and a red eye-mask around its face. I honked twice. The bird 
   I didn't have anything to say to that.                       practically dug its heels and refused to get out of danger. I

114                                                                                                             115

 HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                                         RANDA JARRAR


.swerved to keep from hitting it and, instead, crashed against          and comfortable. I stood there for a long time, until I saw 
 a telephone pole. The windshield's glass cracked slowly but            Keith's Mini Cooper on the horizon. When we approached 
 remained intact, so that when I looked out of,my car, I saw            my crushed car, I imagined the doll head driving it home; 
 everything through a large web of glass flakes.                        imagined Baba and Ibrahim and Jaseem and Waseem wel- 
   I shielded my eyes with my trembling hands and climbed               coming her as though she were me.
 out of my car. The entire hood was accordioned against the               "Stop here a see," I said. Keith pulled up and I got out.
 pole, and both front wheels were spinning slightly off the               I reached into my car and grabbed the mannequin head. 
 ground. I took out my cell phone, but it was useless out               Moda Hair Design College wouldn't be the same with- 
 here, in this rural area. The Crane was still in the middle of         out it. I left the headdress in the backseat. Eventually Was- 
 the street, staring me down behind its red mask.                       eem could hang it up on the miracle wall, between the 
    "Get the hell out of the street," I waved, but it ignored           hummingbird and the peacock sock.
 me.                                                                      We drove to the salon. When we passed Dearborn, I 
    I waited by the side of the road for help, but no one drove         watched the tips of telephone poles, shut-down mills, and 
 by, so I walked up toward the town. It was cold and a little           farther up, the clouds. I reached down to the plastic lever 
 damp, and I dug my hands into my coat. I looked back at my             and leaned my car seat all the way back. And Keith rolled 
 car, and the mannequin head peeked at me behind the bro-               his eyes.
 ken glass. I reached a small gas station where the attendant 
 pointed me to a phone booth in the back.
    I called the cops to file the report, then a tow truck, then 
 my insurance company. At last, I had to figure out what to 
 do with myself. I looked through my phone for numbers, 
 past Baba and jauhara, and landed on Keith. I dialed his 
 number and he picked up at the fourth ring.
    "A fucking duck? In the middle of the streeff
    "A Sandhill Crane," I said.
    "You have the worst luck," he said. "I'll see you in about 
 an hour.>,
    I hung up and stood in the booth. This was how much 
 Palestine my family would inherit. The booth was warm, 


  116                                                                                                                        117

