 TESTIMONY OF MALIK, PRISONER #287690

REPORT
Istanbul, Turkey 
26 December 2015

PRISONER #287690, a kestrel, was found in nearby village 
with Israeli tag on claw and placed under arrest two nights 
ago. Kestrel is scheduled for X-ray in A.M. He is flightless, 
arrested in a small metal cage. We are the assigned guards, 
and very alert. Whenever kestrel stretches out or moves his 
neck, we turn to observe him. We believe the small falcon is 
a spy. We have implanted a chip in his feathers to monitor 
his speech and his whereabouts, in case of escape.

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                            RANDA JARRAR

RECORDED TESTIMONY:                                            which his cast had never seen. This was one of the pebbles 
                                                               he had gathered to throw at the walls of the devil. From then 
COMMANDER T           : What is your name, and are you         on, all the falcons called him El-Hajj Aamer.
a spy?
                                                               COMMANDER T            When were you born.
PRISONER #287690: My name is Malik Kareem Aziz El- 
Hajj Aamer Kan'un. As a child, I saw the bodies of collabo-    PRISONER #287690: Eight years ago. My father took me on 
rators hung from the lines my kin and I used to hunt from.     flights to the Mediterranean, flights that he said were danger- 
Their bodies swayed. The punishment for spying was always      ous because the people living to the west of our village, Israe- 
death. And death never appealed to me.                         lis, carried large guns and monitored their airspace vigilantly. 
                                                               I never questioned why this was, but followed closely behind 
COMMANDER GH            : Your great-grandfather was a         my father's tail. We are small birds of prey, which sometimes 
pilgrim?                                                       works to our advantage: we can go on long-distance flights 
                                                               without arousing too much suspicion. At the Mediterranean, 
PRISONER #287690: Yes, my great-grandfather Aamer per-         I saw humans without feathers swimming in the sea, and hu- 
formed the pilgrimage to Mecca. He flew there from our         mans in large black feathers playing in the sand. My father 
village of Aqraba, over Jerusalem, past the Dead Sea and       explained that the featherless ones were in Tel Aviv, and the 
the ruins of Petra, along the Red Sea, and over Umluj and      feathered ones were in Gaza.
Jeddah, eating grasshoppers and moths, which he hunted 
on the wing, all along the way. Once he arrived in Mecca,      COMMANDER GH            : Were you ever in touch with
he performed the seven rounds around the holy rock, drank      militants in Gaza?
from the water of Zamzam, and flew between Safa and Mar- 
wa. When he came home, my father and his father were re-       PRISONER #287690: No.
lieved to see him—he had been missing for weeks and they 
worried hunters had captured and killed him—but they           COMMANDER GH            : What do you eat? How did
were suspicious of his story, and asked if he could prove that you survive this long journey to Turkey?
he had truly gone on the pilgrimage. My great-grandfather, 
expecting his children and their children to be unbelievers,   PRISONER #287690: My favorite meal is cicadas — fol- 
brought out a rock from his mouth, a pebble the likes of       lowed by voles, butterflies, and grasshoppers. I'll eat a mouse

88                                                                                                            89

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                           RAN DA JARRAR

if I have to. But I prefer songbirds and shrews. Gaza has     I missed my children. My mother was elderly and would al- 
plenty of my favorites. After Father passed, I would go on    low me visits in the early mornings. I asked her if she was 
solo trips to the coast for the cicadas.                      afraid of death, and she said she wasn't. She told me that 
  One day, while I was en route to the sea, I saw the bigger  she had heard that, at death, no one suffers, because each of 
birds, the warplanes, hovering far above me. I knew trouble   us has a pleasant, short hallucination before we let go. This 
was coming, and it did. The plane urinated a white phos-      brought me comfort, as I'm sure it did for her. I hunted voles 
phorous that clouded the air I flew in, and soon I was in the to nourish her, Finding them at night by tracking their urine 
sea. A group of children found me and nursed me to health     lines, which I can find in the pitch dark because I am able 
on the balcony of their apartment. Father always said to stay to see ultraviolet light.
away from humans; they had roasted and eaten some of my         Mother died in winter. We all buried her, my kin mak- 
sisters and brothers. But the children were kind, and bored,  ing peace with me for the day. The children pecked at my 
since they were under curfew. They released me when I was     bracelet, trying to break me free of it. After Mother's death, 
healed.                                                       I left to the sea in Gaza. There was nothing left for me in 
                                                              Aqraba any more.
COMMANDER Z            Why do you have this metal               It had been almost two years since my injury there. And 
bracelet? What contact have you had with Israel?              again, as soon as I arrived, I knew I had come at the wrong 
                                                              time. The large warplanes dropped bombs on balconies, on 
PRISONER #287690: On my flight back to Aqraba, I was          bridges, and on beaches. I could not recognize the building 
captured by university students in Tel Aviv. They took        of the children who had nursed me. It was rubble, I could 
me into their white labs, recorded information about my       not find the children. I could not find cicadas. There were 
feathers, beak, feet, and clipped a metal bracelet on my      no fishermen to accompany at the sea.
leg. They wanted to study my and my family's migration 
patterns. No matter what I did in the months afterwards, I    COMMANDER T           : What did you do then? And did
could not remove the metal bracelet, which had etchings       you return to the Israelis?
on it in their language.
   In Aqraba, everyone was angry with me for being cap-       PRISONER #287690: No. I flew east. I didn't know where 
tured by the Israelis. My wife at the time shat all over our  I was going, I only wanted to leave everything I had known. 
nest, a common message to husbands and humans and             I flew past Aqraba on my way east and it was difficult for me 
other prey to stay away. I respected her wishes, even though  not to land as I always had. I kept flying; lucky for me, I can

90                                                                                                           91

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI                                                                               RANDA JARRAR

fly even in stationary, fixed air. I flew north, toward Cyprus. we watched hippies dance in Syntagma Square, and we ate 
When I arrived there, I found a quarry and had my fill of       the kabobs they left in their wake.
toads, shrews, and snakes. I kept traveling north, arriving in    At the first sign of spring, the anarchist birds got feisty. 
the Aegean Sea. There, I stayed on islands and hunted from      One in particular cautiously declared that she was unsure 
clotheslines and high telephone wires. The local birds paid     about anarchism as a functional social system. The other 
me no mind, neither welcoming nor shunning me. Every            birds laughed and told her that that was the point. Becom- 
morning on the island I liked best, a round, elderly widow      ing braver, she said she had observed a group of bees that 
sat outside her white rock house and watched me through         afternoon who had voted on which place to settle and live 
binoculars. She believed I belonged to her, and I enjoyed her   in. She described their dance, the way the rest of the bees 
sense of ownership over me—it was the closest thing to love.    grew convinced by their bodies' votes. The birds viciously at- 
                                                                tacked her when she said this, pecking at her feathers until 
COMMANDER Z             : Was she Israeli?                      she relented. I flew northeast in the morning.

PRISONER #287690: I don't think so. She was Greek.              COMMANDER Z            : Did you come to Turkey with
                                                                plans to spread anarchy?
COMMANDER GH              : What did you do after that?         PRISONER #287690: Not at all. I flew here to find peace. 
PRISONER #287690: Come winter, the woman left, and              When I arrived in Western Turkey I survived by remembering 
the island's white houses became covered in snow. I wanted      a story about my cousins: they had become famous one 
to fly homeward, but decided to go west to Athens until it      spring and summer by hanging on poles under the flood 
got warmer. In Athens, I lived in Exarchia, with anarchist      lights of a soccer stadium, hunting moths and other insects. 
birds who accepted me so long as I helped them find and         They were recorded doing this and the footage aired around 
share prey. About my metal bracelet they said nothing, only     the world. So, from the air, I looked for stadiums. And I 
that they respected me for escaping the confines of whatever    found them; in their floodlights I hunted and ate to my 
hell the Israelis had made me live in. They smelled awful,      heart's content, watching teenage boys chase soccer balls 
refusing to groom themselves, and had long, tedious conver-     into nets. I kept flying west.
sations about the 1800s, when anarchism was alive and well        That's when I found Istanbul, and the seagulls of Istan- 
in the region. I flew with them to the Acropolis at sunset,     bul. Over the Bosphorous, chasing ferries and being fed by 
and they shat against the Parthenon's walls. In the evenings    humans, I became a cliché: I fell in love. There was no

92                                                                                                               93

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALl                                                                             RANDA JARRAR

difference between her and any of the other gulls. But I flew  insides. We shouted. We whispered. There is nothing inside 
near her every early evening, the sunset athaan being gar-     kestrel—no microphones, no chips. The room empties. He 
bled by the Turkish muatthin, his Arabic awful and funny. I    is placed back in the cage.
told her so, made her laugh. She said we could never breed, 
because I was not one of them. I said that was part of my at-  COMMANDERS T             , GH       and Z 
traction. We were friends through the summer. In early fall,   take notes. CHIEF OF COMMAND E            enters the 
she relocated to the island of Burgazad and I asked if I could room. He stands in front of kestrel, looks into kestrel's eyes.
join.
                                                               CHIEF OF COMMAND E             : We are not afraid of
COMMANDER T            : And did you?                          you. Do you understand?

PRISONER #287690: Her pack did not allow me to. In             PRISONER #287690: Yes. I thought you were talking to 
Karakoy, by the fish market, they zoomed at me from all        me, but then I realized you are speaking in case I really am 
angles, which reminded me of the anti-anarchist bird in        a spy, in case I am recording. But I am not. Upon my honor, 
Athens, her blood, her rebellious stance. They taunted me      I am not.
for my bracelet. They asked where my pack was, said I had 
been left behind on purpose. She did not come to my de-        REPORT, contd. 
fense.                                                         28 December 2015
   I lay bleeding on the rocks near the river. A policeman 
found me and, reading my bracelet, instantly called his        CHIEF OF COMMAND E              takes kestrel out into
commander. The commander and a special terrorism unit          the sun, and releases him.
came and collected me in a cage, ran tests on me all day. 
And now, I am here.                                            FINAL TRANSMISSION FROM PRISONER #287690' S 
                                                               RECORDING CHIP:
REPORT, contd.                                                 17 May 2016
27 December 2015
                                                               I am too elderly to fly home now. I want to return to Aqraba, 
It is now morning and kestrel is sedated. We placed him        to say goodbye, not to those who have shunned me, but 
in the belly of the machine and captured an image of his       to my land, to the olive trees, the earth, and the cicadas.

94                                                                                                             95

HIM, ME, MUHAMMAD ALI

Instead, I live out the rest of my days on the grounds of a 
garden in Topkapi, a beautiful once-palace.
 When death comes, I take comfort in what my mother 
once said.
 But mother lied, because a bitterness fills me, and then — 
the black light.

END REPORT

